<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The recantations as they were seuerallie pronounced by VVylliam Tedder and Anthony Tyrrell (sometime two seminarie priests of the English Colledge in Rome and nowe by the great mercie of almightie God conuerted, vnto the profession of the Gospell of Iesus Christ) at Paules Crosse, the day and yeere as is mentioned in their seuerall tytles of theyr recantations vvith an epistle dedicatorie vnto Her Maiestie and their seuerall præfaces vnto the reader, contayning the causes that mooued them to the same.</title>
            <author>Tedder, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23859.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4937</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24094880</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24094880</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27169</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13565)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27169)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1843:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The recantations as they were seuerallie pronounced by VVylliam Tedder and Anthony Tyrrell (sometime two seminarie priests of the English Colledge in Rome and nowe by the great mercie of almightie God conuerted, vnto the profession of the Gospell of Iesus Christ) at Paules Crosse, the day and yeere as is mentioned in their seuerall tytles of theyr recantations vvith an epistle dedicatorie vnto Her Maiestie and their seuerall præfaces vnto the reader, contayning the causes that mooued them to the same.</title>
                  <author>Tedder, William.</author>
                  <author>Tyrrell, Anthony, 1552-1610? Recantation or abjuration of Anthonie Tyrrell.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Charlewood and VVilliam Brome,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.LXXXVIII [1588]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also published with title: Coppie of a recantation made at Paules Crosse.</note>
                  <note>"The recantation made at Paules Crosse / by William Tedder" and "The recantation or abiuration of Anthonie Tyrrell" each has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: *² A⁴(-A1) B-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27169:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27169:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> Recantations as they were ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallie pronounced by VVylliam Tedder and Anthony Tyrrell: (ſometime two Seminarie Prieſts of the Engliſh Colledge in Rome, and nowe by the great mercie of almightie God conuerted, vnto the profeſſion of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt) at Paules Croſſe, the day and yeere as is mentioned in their ſeuerall Tytles of theyr Recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVith an Epiſtle dedicatorie vnto her Maieſtie, and their ſeuerall Praefaces vnto the Reader, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the cauſes that mooued them to the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <q>NOSCE TE IPSVM. NE QVID NIMIS.</q>
               <p>LOVE AND LYVE</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Charlewood</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by Iohn Charlewood and VVilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Brome. Anno Domini. M.D.LXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:27169:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Queen Elizabeth</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <l>DIûa potens cuius decantant Sydera laudes,</l>
            <l>Quae tibi dante Deo regia ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eptra tenes.</l>
            <l>Pro te pugnantem crûdelis ſenſit Hiberus,</l>
            <l>Qui<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> domi volûit te ſpoliare, Deum.</l>
            <l>Sceptra tibi ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> firma mane<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, et firma manebu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</l>
            <l>Es quoniam f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lix te protegente Deo.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27169:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt noble, vertuous, and gracious Princeſſe, Elizabeth by the grace of God, Queene of England, Fraunce and Irelande, defendreſſe of the fayth. &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">Your Maieſties two late conuerted Subiects (from Papiſme, vnto the profeſſion of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt) Wylliam Tedder &amp; Anthonie Tyrrell, wyſh long health and a moſt proſperous raigne, and finally the eternall health of body and ſoule with Ieſus Chriſt in the worlde to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext vnto the infinite mercie of almightie God (moſt gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne) we haue to thanke your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie that we liue, not onelie this ſhort and tranſitorie life, which is but a paſſage vnto death: but ſo to liue, that we may die to liue for euermore. For what other aſſurance haue we of eternall life, but to die in the true faith of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: of the which, whoſoeuer maketh wracke, it cannot bee but hee muſt perriſh euerlaſtinglie. Howe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerablie we haue beene toſſed on the ſourges of ſchiſmes &amp; deuiſions, howe ſore we haue beene ouerwhelmed with the waues of hereſies, and ouerflowen with the floods of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie and ſuperſtition, howe vnnaturallie we haue beene carried away from our dutifull allegeance, and howe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly we haue beene brought home againe: your Ma. in viewing this ſhort diſcourſe that followeth, in part may vnderſtand. And ſince it hath pleaſed God to conuert vs vnto his trueth, and your highnes to pardon our offences and trecheries paſſed, we can not doubt, but behauing our ſelues like true and perfect paenitents vnto almighty God, and dutifull Subiects vnto your highnes: You will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe
<pb facs="tcp:27169:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> to protect vs for the time to come, againſt all our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and aduerſaries whomſoeuer. Jn hope whereof, wee haue preſumed to preſent your Maieſtie (as a Newe yeeres gift) the firſt fruites of our repentaunce, beſeeching God ſo to endue vs with the gift of perſeueraunce, that we may fructifie better for the time to come. And thus bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loth to offende your Maieſtie with manie words, moſt humbly crauing pardon for this that wee haue doone, wee ende with our humble and hartie prayers, that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie may long liue and raigne ouer vs, to the ſetting forth and aduauncing of Gods moſt holie worde, comfort and conſolation of all good Chriſtians, and confuſion of Antechriſt and all his adhaerents, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto vnfainedlie we ſaie Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your highnes moſt humble and dailie Orators.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Tedder.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anthonie Tyrrell.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27169:3"/>
                  <p>THE Recantation made at Paules Croſſe, by William Tedder Seminarie Prieſt, the firſt of December, Anno. 1588.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>PSALME. 118.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Impulſus euerſus ſum vt caderem, et Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſuſcepit me.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>I was ſore ſhaken that I was like to fall, but the Lord hath vpholden mee.</q>
                  <p>VVherunto is adioyned: The recantation or abiura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Anthonie Tyrell, (ſometime Prieſte of the Engliſh Colledge in Rome,) pronounced by himſelfe at Paules Croſſe the next Sunday following, in the ſame yeere.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seene and allowed according to the order appointed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Printed by Iohn Charlewoode, and VVylliam Brome. Anno. <hi>Dom. 1588.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27169:4"/>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:27169:4"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore you come to the reading of this my recantation, J thought good to aduertiſe you, firſt of the cauſe that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mee to publiſhe it in print, which is the ſatisfaction of all my Countreymen. Firſt, of them that were preſent at the pronouncing of the ſame, for though they did heare mee ſpeake in that place where I did vtter it, yet hearde they not all that heere is ſette down, for the ſhortnes of time cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me to omitt that which I did. Secondly, I haue added ſomething more then was in that copie: ſuch are moſte of the authorities noted in the margent, out of the Scriptures, and certaine verſes, which heere I haue put downe. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, I thought it not ſufficient to haue pronounced it in one place: I know it had beene ſufficient for the aſſembly there preſent: But, my deſire is, that all her Maieſties Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects wherſoeuer, though they heard me not, ſhold haue if it pleaſe them, a copie of my Recantation in theyr hands. Firſt to peruſe for their ſatisfaction. Secondly to prayſe God for myne effectuall conuerſion.</p>
                  <p>I am nowe to entreate the Chriſtian Reader, not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſo much the ſtile wherein I haue written it, as the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection wherewith I did write it: and when you haue ſeene the ſame, I beſeech you to pray God to continue me in that good worke, which his maieſtie hath begun very gratiouſly in mee.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your harty welwiller William Tedder.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27169:5"/>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27169:5"/>
                  <head>¶ The Recantation of William Tedder Seminarie Prieſte, pronounced by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at Paules Croſſe, the firſt of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Anno. 1588.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough euen from my childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode in a manner, I haue béene noſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp in the faith or rather error of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> (bothe my Parents béeing vehemently addicted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame) Yet my fault was ſo much the greater, becauſe I did not onely obſtinatlie, but alſo in a manner deſperatly perſiſt in that Sinagogue againſt mine owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. For I was alwaies diſtracted in minde with doubts of the greateſt points of that Religion. As of the Pope his authoritie. The doctrine of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. The preſumption of fréewill. The fancy of purgatorie. The derogatorie ſacrifice of the Maſſe, and ſuch like. In the which opinions I waded ſo far, that if the helpe of the Lord GOD had not beene at hand, it had béene to mine vtter ruine and confuſion.</p>
                  <p>But ſéeing it hath pleaſed God to call mee backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I will ſay as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.</note> 
                     <hi>If the Lord had not helped me, it had not failed but my ſoule had beene put to ſilence.</hi> Againe, I was in greater faulte, for though I thought they could prooue theſe Articles by authoritie of Counſelles and Fathers, and as they beare men in hand by good reaſons, yet could I finde not ſo much as the grounde of one worde for them in the holy Scriptures. And thus béeing ouerwhelmed with ſo great waters,<note place="margin">Pſal. 69.</note> I was conſtrained to ſay with the Prophet: <hi>I ſticke faſt in the deepe myre where no grounde is, I am come into deepe waters ſo that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27169:6"/> the floods runne ouer mee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thrée cauſes there were which kept me ſo long in mine obſtinancie and errors, which béeing compared with the cauſe of my returning againe, are of no force at all, becauſe they were fooliſh and of men: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was onelie of God, whoſe thoughts are not as the thoughts of men.</p>
                  <p>The firſt of theſe cauſes which turned me ſo farre from the waie, was the great delight that I had in the ſtudie of Naturall Philoſophie. And in this point I was perſwaded, that I ſhoulde more profit in the partes beyond the Seas, then here at home in mine owne natiue Countrey, and therefore, partlie by the inſtigation of my Father, and partlie for the deſyre that I had to ſée forraine Countries, and moſt of all for the loue that I bare vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudie of Philoſophie, I repaired vnto the Countries beyond the Seas, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle conſidering the daungers that might enſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as the diſpleaſure of God, the diſpleaſure of my gracious Prince, and the offence of all my Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond cauſe, was the feare of worldly ſhame and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall diſcredite, for I feared that then, which I finde nowe to bee true: which is, that they which were once my fréendes, would become my mortall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, which by experience I know. I did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider then,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.</note> or els I cared not for that ſentence of our Sauiour: <hi>Euery one that confeſſeth me before men, the ſonne of man ſhall confeſſe him before the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God. And hee that denyeth mee before men, hee alſo ſhalbe denied before the Angels of GOD.</hi> This was the cauſe that made mee to take a prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous waie, turning all things to mine own credit, when I ſhould haue turned them to the glorie of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God,<note place="margin">Matt. 6,</note> for our Sauiour ſaith: <hi>Firſt ſeeke the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27169:6"/> of God and the righteouſnes of the ſame, and all other things ſhalbe giuen vnto you.</hi> Thus think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to get credit by mine obſtinacie, I did looſe the fauour of God, the loue of my Soueraigne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, and the good will of all true ſubiects, which I hope to recouer againe, by this my frée Recantation, and my further conuerſation from henceforth in my Countrey.</p>
                  <p>The third cauſe, was the tickling of vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and this cauſe I am ſure doth detaine moſt of the contrarie ſide in their peruerſe obſtinacie, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they bragge that they ſéeke nothing by their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings but the glorie of God. For, I was not mooued a little to ſubmitt my ſelfe to her Maieſties mercie, and to embrace the knowledge of the true fayth, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wicked counſell and deuilliſh deuiſes of the Pope and his Children, againſt the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, and our moſt déere Countrey. Which counſels I thought they woulde neuer haue put in execution. But when I ſaw that great prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe come to paſſe, I meane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuaſion of this Land, God ſo moouing me (as héereafter I will manifeſt) I thought vtterlie to forſake them, although couertlye for vaine gloryes ſake I continued a while amongſt them. I thought it then a goodly thing, and woorthy of commendation for mee, to defend an euill cauſe by probable reaſons. Yet I knew it was an hard thing for <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> to prooue that Snowe was blacke, or yncke white,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> and for me to prooue light to be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or darknes to be light. For it is written, <hi>I wyll deſtroy the wiſedome of the wiſe, and caſt away the vnderſtanding of the prudent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now, ſéeing it hath pleaſed almighty God, to call me to the knowledge of his trueth,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> in deteſtation of this vaine glorie, I will ſaie with the Apoſtle: <hi>Si
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27169:7"/> gloriari oportet, quae infirmitatis meae ſunt gloriabo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> that is, <hi>If I muſt needes boaſt, I will boaſt in mine infyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12</note> And againe, <hi>Libenter gloriabor in infirmitatibus meis, vt inhabitet in me virtus Chriſti:</hi> that is, <hi>I wyll gladlie boaſt in mine infirmities, that the power of Chriſt may dwell within me.</hi> Thus haue I bréefely declared the cauſes which draue me out of the waie, and cauſed me to delight in vanities, and follow lyes ſo long,<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> that if Gods grace had not béene, I had béen cléene caſt awaie. But, now I ſaie againe, <hi>Impulſus euerſus ſum vt caderem et dominus ſuſcepit me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 118</note> 
                     <hi>I was ſore ſhaken that I was like to fall, but the Lorde hath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden mee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But héere you will aſke mee the cauſe of ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine a change: I aunſwere, that I knowe no other but the grace of almightie GOD, the which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth when and as it pleaſeth him. This grace haue I often refuſed for the cauſes before alledged: me thought I heard him ſaie vnto me dailie, <hi>Ecce ſto ad oſtium et pulſo,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Apo. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold I ſtand knocking at thy dores.</hi> Yet was I not aſhamed to thruſt him out, and to let in his aduerſarie the deuill. I hearde him cry within mée,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Aperi mihi ſoror mea, amica mea, Columba mea, immaculata mea, caput meum plenum eſt rore, et cincinni mei guttis noctium: <hi>Ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me my ſiſter, my friend, my Doue, my vnſpotted, my head is full of dew, and my locks with the droppes of the night.</hi>
                     </hi> I heard him giue me theſe louing titles, but I refuſed him &amp; gaue him this aunſwer:<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
                     <hi>Expoliani me tunica mea, quomodo induar illa? Laui pedes meos quomodo coinquinabo illos? <hi>I haue put off my coate, howe ſhall I put it on again? I haue waſhed my feete, howe ſhall I defile them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</hi>
                     </hi> Thus continued I, vntill hee by his grace ſo ſwéetly and forcibly preuented me, that whether I would or not, at length hee compelled my revellious
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27169:7"/> wyll to obey. So that I which once did ſo little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the true and auncient faith, that I counted it for an hereſie: now I ſée euidentlie, that without the ſame there is no waie to ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, if euer you pittied anie mans caſe, I beſéeth you haue compaſſyon vpon mine, conſidering that it is a thing incident to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature to erre and to ſin, but to continue and perſiſt in it, is the parte of the deuill. I freelie doo confeſſe &amp; acknowledge that I haue ſinned againſt God, my Prince,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> and my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as a man whoſe nature is prone, &amp; the thoughts of whoſe hart is alwaies bent to miſchiefe, I perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in mine errours a long time, as one that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſuggeſtions of the Serpent, rather then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations of the ſpirit of God. But by his motion, I am returned againe to the ſhéepfold of Chriſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I requeſt you all, for the tender mercies of God, that you would receiue mee that returne againe, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ſteps of our Sauiour:<note place="margin">Luk. 15</note> who diſdained not to receiue Publicans and ſinners: who left <hi>99.</hi> ſhéepe in the wildernes and went to ſéeke one that was loſt. I haue béen like the prodigall Son, which looſely and want onlie ſpent his portion in ryot &amp; luſte, and was compelled to eate ſuch meate as the Hogges did. All this haue I doone, I haue ſpent that Talent which God gaue me, in maintaining the harlot of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in vpholding the chaire of peſtilence, I meane the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I haue fed my ſelfe with the ſwill and dregs of mens inuentions and traditions, forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the fountaine and foode of Gods worde. All this I haue doone: but at the laſt béeing by hunger com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled, I cryed out with that prodigall child, ſaying: <hi>Pater peccaui in caelum et coram te,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 15</note> 
                     <hi>iam non ſum dignus vocari filius tuus: <hi>Father I haue ſinned againſt heauen and before thee, I am not woorthy to bee called anie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27169:8"/> more thy Son.</hi>
                     </hi> This confeſſion mooued his Father to compaſſion, who louingly embraced him, receiued him willinglie, and cheriſhed him tenderlie. So I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you not to refuſe me, though I come late home, receiue me againe, and haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion. For our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Matt. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Beati miſericordes quoniam ipſi mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiam conſequentur, <hi>Bleſſed are the mercifull for they ſhall obtaine mercie.</hi>
                     </hi> And truely to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion is a thing wherein a man dooth followe the example of almightie GOD, for Chriſte himſelfe doth ſay,<note place="margin">Luke. 6</note> 
                     <hi>Eſtote miſericordes ſicut pater veſter miſericors eſt, <hi>Be you mercifull as your Father is mercifull.</hi>
                     </hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue me I beſéech you which was a fugitiue, as one that repenteth, as one that deſireth rather to bee an abiect in Gods houſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.</note> then to dwell in the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of ſinners. His name therefore who hath ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully called me, be bleſſed for euermore.</p>
                  <p>But nowe I will come to the purpoſe, that is, to recant and renounce ſuch errours, as heeretofore I haue maintained, deſiring God, that as it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his heauenly goodnes to giue me the grace to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, ſo it would alſo pleaſe him, to giue me the gift of perſeuerance to continue, that I may no more fall into them againe.</p>
                  <p>You knowe it is the nature of the Serpent, to kéepe his head whole though he put his body in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for the defence of the ſame: but, if a man once bruſe his head, he can no longer endure againſt him but he muſt of neceſſitie die. And I can no better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the huge and weldie maſſe of Papiſtrie to anie thing, then vnto a Serpent, therefore in renouncing of it I will begin with the head.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The firſt Article of the Pope.</note>The Papiſts doo think, and I did thinke the ſame, that the Pope was Chriſt his Vicar, and ſupreame head of the vniuerſall Church héere vppon the earth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27169:8"/> militant. This Article béeing mightily vpholden, and ſtoutly defended, they thinke none other of their Bulwarks can be ſhaken. They thinke alſo that hee hath ſuch a prerogatiue, that he cannot erre, whereof ryſeth this preſumption in depoſing of Princes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gradation of Biſhops, excomunication of all ſortes of people without reſpect, and of moſt light occaſion.</p>
                  <p>Héereof hee preſumeth to preſcribe Lawes to the whole Church, the which forſooth without his dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation muſt be inuiolable, <hi>Sub pena excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</hi> And whoſoeuer dooth breake them, if it be Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, King, Quéene, or what Prince ſoeuer, he muſt be depoſed, ſuch wickednes hath he practized againſt the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, to his vtter ſhame and confuſion, that the Prouerbe may bee ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, God ſendeth a ſhrewde Cowe ſhorte hornes. But his holines, if it pleaſe you, is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with this: hee chalengeth to himſelfe ſo great a preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, that hee wyll make and deface Articles of the Fayth at his owne will and pleaſure.<note place="margin">Gratian.</note> 
                     <hi>Quia Dominus Deus noſter Papa.</hi> Héereof it ariſeth, that in that Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, ſcarce any of the Laye people can tel what they beléeue: for béeing aſked a reaſon of their faith, they ſaie nothing els, but thus beléeueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churche, thus ſaith the Pope. Whereas in deede, the reaſon of our Faith ſhould be taken from the word of God, for as the Pſalmiſt ſaith: <hi>Omnis homo mendax,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 116</note> 
                     <hi>Euery man is a lyer.</hi> And therefore it ſhal ſuffiſe me that the Pope is a man, and conſequently a lyer, and may not onelie erre, but alſo hath already erred, which if I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired not to be briefe I woulde prooue, vnles by thys his ſupreame vſurped authority he be deified or made a God, which thing to confeſſe is not onely impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie but alſo intollerable blaſphemie. I therefore doe héere vtterly deteſt, abiure, and renounce him, with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27169:9"/> all his excommunications, interdictions, ſuſpenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, degradations, depoſitions, irregularities and a thouſand ſuch like trifling thunderbolts. I pronounce alſo his doctrine, not to be according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but contrarie vnto it, and therefore I doo freely and ioyfullie recant it, thanking GOD that it hath pleaſed his di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ne Maieſtie to deliuer mee from the ſlauery of that Tyrant, deſiring him alſo that I may not fall into his ſubiection againe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2 Of the Maſſe.</note>Next vnto this is their blaſphemous doctrine of theyr Propitiatorie ſacrifice, which they cal the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſſe. This Maſſe I once did deuoutlie thinke vpon, hearde with great attention, and with great reuerence I did celebrate, onelie becauſe I thought it was indeede a ſacrifice, propitiatorie both for the liuing and the deade: when as the Scripture plainlie teſtifieth,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> that <hi>Chriſtus ſemel pro peccatis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris mortuus eſt, iuſtus pro iniuſtis, vt nos offecret Deo, mortificatos quidem carne, viuificatos autem ſpiritu. <hi>Chriſt once died for our ſinnes, the iuſt for them that were vniuſt, that he might offer vs vp to God, morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in fleſhe, but quickned in ſpirite.</hi>
                     </hi> Hetherto alſo dooth all the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> tende. It was alſo commaunded the High Prieſt in the olde Law, that hee ſhoulde enter into <hi>Sancta Sanctorum</hi> but once in the yéere, which ſimilitude the Apoſtle, in the ſame Epiſtle, applyeth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely ſacrifice which Chriſt offered for our ſins vpon the Croſſe. The which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath once doone, I think it vnlawful to haue any more propitiatorie Sacrifices then that one of our Sauiour Chriſt. And therefore that which they call the propitiatory Sacrifice of the Maſſe, I thinke it rather to be a derogatorie blaſphemie to the paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſt. And for that cauſe I denie that either it is a Sacrifice, or auailable for the lyuing,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27169:9"/> much leſſe for the dead I do alſo from henceforth vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly denounce it to be wicked, and an Idoll.</p>
                  <p>Tranſubſtantiation,<note place="margin">3 Of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, and reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</note> a terme inuented in the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane Counſell,</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thyrde of that name, to eſtabliſh an other error as groſſe as it ſelfe, that is to ſay: The Reall preſence of Chriſte his bodie in the Sacrament (as they call it) of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar: is contrarie not onelie to Fayth, but alſo to natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon. For the holy Scripture teacheth vs, that <hi>Chriſt is aſcended into heauen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mar. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; ſitteth at the right hand of God.</hi> And alſo that it was thought conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that heauen ſhould containe him,<note place="margin">Act. 3.</note> not according to his diuinitie, which is incomprehenſible, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his humane nature which is circumſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or to bee contained in one place, for he tooke not onelie the bodie of man vpon him, but alſo the paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a naturall bodie, and therefore hath his proper place. But if they will néedes haue him preſent in manie places at once, they muſt alſo denie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath a bodie, and conſent to the <hi>Eutichian</hi> hereſey, and ſaie there was a commiſſion of the diuine and humaine nature, which <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Creede denieth,<note place="margin">Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Neque commiſtionem paſſus, neque diuiſionem, <hi>ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuffering mixture nor diuiſion.</hi>
                     </hi> Yet of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was I neuer ſo fully perſwaded, but that ſtill I had ſome doubt of it. And now I renounce it, crauing pardon of God, for defending that which I alwayes doubted of.</p>
                  <p>The number of the Sacraments in the Church,<note place="margin">4 Number of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> I acknowledge is no more then two, that is to witt, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper, and theſe two I finde to be inſtituted by Chriſt himſelfe in the holye Goſpell. The other fiue which they adde, which are, Confirmation, Penaunce, Extreame vnction, Order, and Matrimonie. Becauſe I know not where to find
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27169:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> them, neither by the inſtitution of Chriſt, nor in the Goſpell or Newe Teſtament, I count them not for Sacraments: for I thinke none to haue authority to make Sacraments but God onely, and therfore thoſe two I thinke to be Sacraments and none other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">5 Prayer to Saints.</note>They make a great ſtriuing and ſtrugling to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Prayer, and inuocation to the Saints depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, thinking the mediation of our Lorde and Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Ieſus Chriſt inſufficient for vs: This inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I did thinke béeing in that Sinagogue, to bee a neceſſarie and a conuenient thing, although for the ſame I coulde finde no ground in the word of GOD. Yet one thing in the ſame, béeing as I thought then an abuſe, I knewe not howe to excuſe: and that was the inuocation of diuers Saints for diuers purpoſes. As, one againſt the plague, as S. <hi>Sebaſtian.</hi> An other againſt the tootheake, as S. <hi>Appolonia.</hi> Another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the falling ſicknes, as S. <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> and dyuers other. As though almightie God coulde not heare vs but by the helpe of theſe Saints. And thus in calling vpon them, we derogate from the glorie of almightie God. But they ſay, they deſire them but to pray for them, and aſke no other grace at theyr handes. Then woulde I gladly knowe of them why they vſe theſe verſes in theyr office of S. <hi>Peter ad vincula.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Solue iubente deo terrarum Petre cathenas,</l>
                     <l>Qui facis vt pateant caeleſtia regna beatis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>In Engliſh thus,
<q>
                        <l>O Peter looſe as God commaunds, from vs the earthly chayne,</l>
                        <l>The which to bleſſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doſt make, the gate of heauen plaine.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>☞ And in a Hymne of the ſame.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Iam bone paſtor Petre clemens accipe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ota precantum et peccati vincula,</l>
                     <l>Reſolue tibi poteſtate tradita,</l>
                     <l>Qua cunctis caelum verbe claudis aperis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:27169:10"/>
                  <p>In Engliſh thus.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nowe ſheepeheard good, ô Peter milde receiue,</l>
                     <l>The vowes with prayer which we yeeld to thee:</l>
                     <l>By that ſame power which God to thee did giue,</l>
                     <l>Which mak'ſt the skyes be ſhut, and wide to bee.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>One thing I meruaile at, that as yet the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries béeing in controuerſie, whether the Saints do ſée God or not, and yet graunting that Saints can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare the praiers of the liuing but by the ſight of God, why ſo obſtinatly they defende this point? And nowe, whereas before I counted it neceſſarie &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, I count it vaine, and ſuperfluous, and take it for an errour.</p>
                  <p>Againe, prayer for the deade,<note place="margin">6 Prayer for the dead</note> is a point of great Religion amongſt them: which Article they ground vpon an other no leſſe abſurde then it ſelfe, and that is Purgatorie, which Purgatorie I ſée not vowe they can defende by Scripture, though they ſéeme contentiouſly to wreſt certaine places of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, from the true meaning of the ſame vnto theyr owne meaning, and all to defende this groſſe errour of theirs. For they ſay that thoſe ſoules that depart out of this life with anie veniall ſinne, or els with the Reliques of mortall ſinne: muſt néedes bee pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged after this life before they can came to Heauen.</p>
                  <p>This is a groſſe error and is taken out of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et <hi>Virgil,</hi> for in that place where hee bringeth <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes,</hi> to enſtruct his Sonne <hi>Aeneas</hi> of theyr ſtate in hell, he ſpeaketh on the ſort.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Quin et ſupremo cum lumine vita reliquit</l>
                     <l>Non tamen omne malum miſeris,<note place="margin">Aeneid. 6.</note> nec funditus omnes</l>
                     <l>Corporea excedunt peſtes, penituſque neceſſe eſt,</l>
                     <l>Multa diu concreta modis violeſcere miris.</l>
                     <l>Ergo excutentur paenis, veterumque malorum</l>
                     <l>Supplina expendunt, alia pautuntur inanes,</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:27169:11"/>
                     <l>Suſpenſae ad uentos, aliis ſub gurgite vaſto</l>
                     <l>Infectum eli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>itur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>bis, aut exuritur igni,</l>
                     <l>Quiſque ſuos patimur manes, exinde per amplum</l>
                     <l>Mittimur Elyſium et pauci laeta arua tenemus.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>In Engliſh thus.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>And alſo when the pleſant life is gone with gladſome light,</l>
                     <l>Yet euery miſchiefe from thoſe ſoules is not departed quite,</l>
                     <l>Nor plague of body yet is gone, and ſo it needfull is,</l>
                     <l>That many things ſhould them deſteine which once haue been amis.</l>
                     <l>Therfore they ſuffer puniſhment, &amp; for offences paſt,</l>
                     <l>They haue their meed, of bluſtring winds, ſome feele the bitter blaſt</l>
                     <l>And ſome in botto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a gulfe do waſh their faults away,</l>
                     <l>And ſome with flames of ſcorching fire, for paſſed ſins do pay,</l>
                     <l>Each one of vs his paine doth feele, and then exempt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine,</l>
                     <l>We walk about theſe pleaſant fields a very little trayne.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>This Article therfore with the reſt, is ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, vaine and ridiculous.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">7. Workes of Supere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation,</note>Workes of ſupererogation as they call them, are ſo vaine and fooliſh, that I meruaile that wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men at anie time will confeſſe any ſuch to bee. For the holie Scripture ſayth, that when we haue doone all that we can, we muſt call our ſelues vnprofitable ſeruaunts. Truelie for my part, I knowe not why they ſhould ſo bind God vnto our works, that if wée doo them, he cannot chooſe but ſaue vs. For all that we can doo commeth from God, and we are bound to followe, and accept of the good inſpirations of him. But this worde Supererogation, dooth ſignifie that the worke which we doo, is more then we are bound to doo, which taketh awaie the grace of God as the <hi>Pelagean</hi> dooth, and fortifieth our fréewill ſo much, as though it had neuer béen loſt. But truely I think and beléeue our Fréewill to be ſo wounded, that not onely it is not able to doo more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ought, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it can not performe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we ought to doo. Let them of the aduerſary part contend and wrangle ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo much to the contrarie. The grounde of thys
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27169:11"/> their vngrounded doctrine,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.</note> is taken out of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the <hi>Samaritane,</hi> which tooke compaſſion vpon him, who diſcending from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Iericho,</hi> was wounded by Théeues. For paying the Hoſte of the houſe for his charges, he told him that whatſoeuer he laid out more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had giuen him, at his return he would pay him againe. Yet conſider they not, that in that Parable our Sauiour exhorteth vs to mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue &amp; neighbourly charitie, and that euery man is bounde to doo good vnto his neighbour in time of néede.</p>
                  <p>They denie that faith is ſufficient to iuſtifie vs in Gods ſight, without our owne merits,<note place="margin">8 Good woorkes.</note> contrary to the doctrine of the Apoſtle in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines,</hi> and <hi>Galathians.</hi> For good works are indeede required at our handes, not as the cauſe, but as the effect of our iuſtification. And for this cauſe workes are required at our hands, to be a teſtimonie of our Faith, and a cauſe that other men may giue the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto God: for our Sauiour ſaith,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Sic luceat lux veſtra coram hominibus, vt videant opera veſtra bona et glorificent Patrem veſtrum qui eſt in caelis. <hi>So let your light ſhyne before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heauen.</hi>
                     </hi> Then is it conſequent, that our iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth no waies of our ſelues, but onely by faith in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>After this followeth a moſt ridiculous doctrine,<note place="margin">9 Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences and pardons.</note> of the Popes Indulgences and pardons, wherein he dooth moſt inſolently arrogate to himſelf, the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of Chriſt his paſſion, applying that to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of ſins, the forme of which hath an arrogant kind of ſpéech, as thus. If a man faſt one Friday with bread and water, he ſhal haue <hi>plenarie indulgence,</hi> and if he faſt ſo on another day, his pardon ſhalbe limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:27169:12"/> for certaine yéeres, as 10000. &amp;c. or ſome ſuch like, or els <hi>a pena et culpa.</hi> I alwaies thought theſe trifles vaine, but now I ſée the blaſphemie of them. For it is ſcant poſſible to get theſe great Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but by wearing a paire of Beades, or a Graine, Medall, Crucifixe, Picture, <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> or ſuch like tromperie. It would be too tedious to ſet downe the manifold kinds of theſe Indulgences, which al tend to one ende, that is, to the leſſening of the vertue of Chriſt his paſſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">10 Images. <hi>Exo. 20.</hi>
                     </note>The ſeconde commaundement plainly forbiddeth vs to make or to haue any grauen Image, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of any thing to worſhip it. But the aduerſarie excommunicateth them that denie the neceſſitie of Images in Churches, as it is to be ſéene in dyuers of their Counſels. For ſay they, it is lawfull, not onlie to retaine them, but alſo to worſhip the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The which if it be not againſt the ſeconde commaundement, let them looke vnto it, I for mine owne part doo ſée it, and am aſhamed that euer I was ſo blockiſh, as to thinke a block or a ſtone to bee neceſſarie or godlie, I thought it ſo once, but nowe I cannot be ſo perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For he that hath any reaſon in him to diſcourſe, or ſence to perceiue, cannot be ſo void of reaſon, or ſo ſenceleſſe as to exhibit honor or reuerence to a ſenc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Image, when the ſame Image, if it had ſence, would not onely refuſe that worſhip, but alſo would willingly fall downe to worſhip or adore the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that made it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">11 Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in both kinds</note>They hold and defend that the Laye people may not receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Communion vnder both kinds, which doctrine is repugnant to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtitution of Chriſt. For he ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that were preſent with him at hys laſt Supper, <hi>Take and eate, and drinke ye all of this.</hi> For though the aduerſary ſay, that the Laye people
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27169:12"/> haue not the priuiledge to receiue the Cup, becauſe the Apoſtles who onely were preſent at that ſupper were Prieſtes, and not Laye men: it holdeth not, for by the ſame reaſon, a man may alſo barre the Laye people from receiuing of either kinde, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles were Prieſts, and only preſent at the Supper, <hi>ergo</hi> it is vnlawful for any to be pertaker of that Supper but onlie Prieſts. And yet Chriſt himſelfe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Vnles you eate my fleſh and drinke my blood, you ſhall haue no life in you.</hi> And theſe words he ſpake not only to the Apoſtles, but <hi>Turbis Iudeorum,</hi> to the company of the Iewes, and therfore I count their dealings iniurious to the people, their doctrine blaſphemous, &amp; their proofe to no purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Finallie, all ſuch Articles,<note place="margin">12 Dyuers other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</note> which are repugnaunt to the word of God: I vtterly refuſe, as in ſpeciall, the Seruice in an vnknowne tongue, the prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the reading of Scriptures to the Laye people, the forbidding of the tranſlation of the ſame into a vulgare tongue, Pylgrimages, Vowes, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, all ſuch Articles, as are contrarie to the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Religion, ſet downe by publique authoritie, I doo vtterly renounce and abiure: and on the other ſide, I doo willingly, and without compulſion, and gladly with reuerence, receiue, embrace, and fréelie profeſſe, the ſayde Articles ſet forth by publique au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as doctrine without ſuperſtition, and moſt agréeable to the word of God.</p>
                  <p>Thus haue I generally recanted mine errours in matters of Religion, and nowe, will I accuſe my ſelfe and my dealings, touching my diſobedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my Soueraigne the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie. I haue moſt ſtubbornly and wilfullye tranſgreſſed her Maieſties Lawes. Knowing firſt the offence of going beyond the Seas, and yet caring
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27169:13"/> not for that, I procéeded further, and willinglie was prieſted at <hi>Rome.</hi> Thirdly, maliciouſly I came into my Countrey, with a will to ſeduce her Ma. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from the true and ſincere Religion, and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubiects to that tyranny, vnto the which I was my ſelfe ſubiect. Then being baniſhed, I returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into my Countrey, with the ſame intent that I came in firſt, and for theſe great faultes of myne I am moſt hartily ſorrie, and in the bowels of Gods infinite mercy, I deſire all them, that any waies by my meanes haue béene deceiued, &amp; doo nowe repent, to forgiue me. Likewiſe thoſe that haue not as yet their harts mooued by my example, to forſake theyr errours and amend their opinions.</p>
                  <p>Thus firſt of all I aſke forgiuenes of almightie God, whom like a moſt ingratefull &amp; wilful wretch, I haue moſt gréeuouſly offended. Firſt, in abuſing his gifts, which of his fatherly goodnes he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon me. Secondly, in refuſing and reiecting his holy inſpirations. And laſtly, by prouoking o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to offend by my example. And all this haue I doone, not like vnto them, vnto whom our Sauiour promiſeth a milder iudgment in the latter day: but like vnto them of whom S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> Which when they knew God, did not honor him as GOD was to be honoured, and therfore my damnation had béene the greater if I had perſiſted. But ſéeing that it hath pleaſed him, which hath preſerued mee from my Mothers, wombe to call mee to his wonderfull light, I deſire you all that are héere preſent, to giue him thankes for the ſame: for there is more ioy in heauen before the Angels of God,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> for the conuerſion of one ſinner, then for <hi>99.</hi> iuſt perſons which neede no repentaunce. Deſiring alſo his diuine Maieſtie, that he would not remember mine olde wickednes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27169:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> and follie:<note place="margin">Pſal. 143</note> for if he would enter into iudgment with his Seruants, there ſhoulde none be iuſtified in hys ſight. But that he would think on the paſſion of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, by the which hee hath moſt mercifully redéemed mee, deſiring him alſo, that it hath pleaſed his diuine Maieſtie, to call mee to the light of his trueth: ſo it woulde pleaſe him to bring al them which now do liue in blindnes, to the ſame. Secondly, with humble hart I aſke forgiuenes of the Quéenes Maieſtie, moſt humbly ſubmitting my ſelfe to the mercy of ſo godly a Prince, whom when ſhe called her Subiects to their duetie &amp; obedience, not by ſeueritie and rigor of the Law, but like a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull mother, by mercie: I haue not onely not heard her, but alſo, (with ſorrow I ſpeake it) I haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and ſet light by.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, I aſke forgiuenes of you that bee héere preſent, in whom I thinke that I ſée all my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen preſent: deſiring you to forgiue all ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, as I haue committed againſt GOD, the Quéenes Maieſtie, and againſt you.</p>
                  <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27169:14"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:27169:14"/>
                  <p>THE Recantation or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration of Anthonie Tyrrell: (ſometime Prieſt of the Engliſhe Colledge in Rome, but nowe by the great mercie of God conuerted, and become a true profeſſor of his word.) Pronounced by himſelfe at Paules Croſſe, after the Sermon made by M. Pownoll Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: the eight of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. 1588.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>IERE. 31. verſe, 19.</bibl> 
                     <hi>Poſtquam conuertiſti me, egi paenitentiam: et poſtquam oſtendiſti mihi percuſsi faemur meum.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q>After thou haddeſt conuerted me (O Lord) I did repent: and after that thou hadſt ſhewed me the grauitie of my ſinne, I ſtroke my thygh for ſhame.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Séene and allowed according to the order appointed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Printed by Iohn Charlewoode and VVylliam Brome. <hi>1588.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:27169:15"/>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:27169:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Recantation made at Paules Croſſe the day &amp; yere aboue written, is nowe publiſhed. I thought it expedient (good Chriſtian Reader) to ſet out together withal, this ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe by waie of Praeface, for theſe reſpects which followe. Firſt, that I might make a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie of ſuch neceſſarie points, which at the time of making my Recantation, (hauing but halfe an howre allowed me) I was enforced to omitt. Secondlie, that euerie good man, vnto whom the viewe of my recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſhall come, might thorowlie be ſatisfied of my vnfained meaning in the performance of this action: the which as it concerneth the euerlaſting health or detriment of my ſoule, ſo of all other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I were moſt miſerable and wretched, if I ſhould anie waies be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with hipocriſie or diſſimulation. Thirdlie, that I might the better ſtop the ſlaunderous reports of the aduerſarie whom I haue forſaken, whoſe pens and ſpeeches (I am ſure) will nowe bee ſo much the more vehement &amp; ſharpe againſt me, by how much I am miraculouſly eſcaped and deliuered from them, who no doubt wil ſeeke to obſcure the glory of God in this his wonderfull and prouident worke, and to defame me for the furtheraunce of their owne cauſe, all that they can.</p>
                  <p>Theſe reſpects mooued me to adde ſome-thing more for the perfectyng of the thing, that neyther that which I had purpoſed to haue ſpoken, might be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27169:16"/> vnſayd, the Reader better ſatisfied, and the aduerſarie ouerthrowen.</p>
                  <p>As concerning the firſt poynt, wheras I could not in ſo ſmall a portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of time, ſet downe the cauſes that mooued me firſt to forſake the Pope, to ſuſpecte his religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to make my vnſayned ſubmiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, together with the cauſes that brought me back againe: what the ſhortnes of time then forced me to omit, heere now I haue ſupplyed by my penne.</p>
                  <p>The firſt and principall thing that mooued me to forſake the Pope, and to contemne his religion, (next vnto the great mercie and prouidence of almightie God) was his notorious trecheries &amp; vngodly prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, againſt our moſte gracious Queene and Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne: vnto the happie conſideration wherof I came not, vntil ſuch time as it pleaſed God to ſtoppe me of my courſe, (which was in raunging vppe and downe her Maieſties Realme, in ſowing the ſeed not only of falſe doctrine, but alſo of ſedition and rebellion) and bringing me into priſon for as it is written, <hi>Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio dat intellectum, Tribulation giueth vnderſtanding:</hi> &amp; finding my ſelf within the daunger of her Maieſties lawes: I began better to conſider the cauſe and quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel that I had taken in hand, remembring that ſaying of <hi>Cyprian: Non<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> paena ſed cauſa facit martyrem,</hi> that is <hi>Not the payne but the cauſe maketh a Martir.</hi> I found that my cauſe did more concerne the Pope then any Religion, and that rather I was to be conuicted for matter of high Treaſon, then to be perſecuted with any extremitie for matter of meere conſcience: For that all the world knoweth, that her Maieſtie neuer did put any to death for matter of meere conſcience or Religion.</p>
                  <p>In the conſideration of my cauſe, which cheefely was for the defence of the Pope: I remembred how
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27169:16"/> 
                     <hi>Pius</hi> the 5. had exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated her Ma. &amp; remoued ſo many of her ſubiects fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their dutiful &amp; natural o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, as ſtoode perſwaded of the authority of his accurſſed cenſure: the which (to ſpeak truly) my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience alwayes deteſted, &amp; hardly could my ſtomack be brought to dygeſt ſuch an vnſauourye pill, vntill ſuch time as by falſe perſwaſion, I was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taminate al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together. Beeing therfore (as I ſayd) brought by the prouidence of God into priſon: I came into this hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pie conſideration, that the defending of the Pope his quarrell: would rather make me a Traitour then a Martir, &amp; that my cauſe would ſooner prooue high Treaſon, then true Religion. For remembring the cauſe and effect of the Pope his exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating of her Maieſtie: I found it was nothing els, but to diſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſe her of her Crowne &amp; Royaltie, &amp; that Doctor <hi>Moorton,</hi> a man of little learning, and leſſe Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, after that he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e into <hi>England</hi> to publiſh the ſame, who trauelling all the North partes: gaue authority generally vnto all the Prieſtes, to perſwade her Ma. Subiects, as well in <hi>foro conſcientiae,</hi> as in <hi>foro exteriori,</hi> (as they tearme it) to withdrawe their naturall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from their Prince, and to prepare them ſelues for rebellion. What effect this Excommunication wrought: the ſequell declared by the Northen rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. I remembred alſo, that Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him: dealt a great deale more ſubtilly, &amp; more dangerouſly then his predeceſſour, for wheras Pope <hi>Pius</hi> had excommunicated her Ma. openly: <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13. diſpenſed with all Papiſts, that it might be law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full outwardly to profeſſe obedience, and to acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge her Ma. their lawfull Queene &amp; Soueraigne: and yet inwardly to retayne a traiterous minde, and to practiſe all the tretcheries againſt her that they can. Examples of this matter I need not produce: the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:27169:17"/> and confeſſions of ſuch as haue been executed for their treaſons, can well witnes. I conſidered more ouer, the ſending of <hi>Saunders</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> with a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany of ſtrangers for an inuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; how that <hi>Stukeley</hi> had beene imployed to the ſame purpoſe, had he not been as falſe to the Pope, as he was to his Soueraigne. Theſe &amp; the like conſiderations, at what time I was firſt committed pryſoner into the Counter, made me to ſuſpect mine owne cauſe, &amp; quarrell that I had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hand, and God aſſiſting mee with his grace, I humbled my ſelfe, and did write a Letter of ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto an honorable Counſeller of this Realme, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom I dyſcouered my knowledge of ſuch vile &amp; horrible practiſes, as I did knowe to be intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her Ma. and the ſtate. I diſlyked the Pope &amp; his Religson, that noſeled men vp in ſuch abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable treaſons, and deſired to be better enſtructed in matters of faith and ſaluation, and that I might come vnto a more true and godly profeſſion, then before I was brought vp in. My petition was fauourably ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, I was not only pardoned mine offences: but I was alſo reſtored into grace and fauour: And thys was the firſt time.</p>
                  <p>Thus hauing declared the firſt &amp; principall cauſe, that moued me to forſake the Pope and to exchange my religion: I ſhall in a woord or two ſet downe the cauſes that made mee to fall backe againe, the which (next vnto the prouidence of almightie God, that ſo had appointed it) was, as I breefly repeated in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation, my corrupt affection: For hauing all the dayes of my life been trayned vp among Papiſts, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in their Schooles, and hearing continuallye their Sermons, reading their Bookes, and giuing my minde little or nothing vnto the ſtudie of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, refuſing alwayes either to heare or to read any
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27169:17"/> thing that might contrary my firſt conceiued opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and hauing all my freendes &amp; acquaintance of the Papiſts parte, thinking that I ſhould be left deſolate and naked when I were departed from them, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more regard vnto the ſhame &amp; obloquie of the world, for altering my religion, then vnto the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of a good conſcience for my godly and wel doing, and not being ſo thankfull vnto almightie God for ſo great a benefit receiued, as I ought, or ſo carefull to preſerue my ſelfe from the daunger of falling into the like offence agayne, not hauing my ſoule thorowlye clenſed from the dregges of corrupt affection: And falling into the companye of ſuch, as I could not bee but greatly endangered by them, partly by perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and partly by flatterie, partlye by fayre promiſes, &amp; partly by intreaty: I was at the length ſo bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as (forgetting my dutie vnto God, my allegeance vnto my Prince, and looue vnto my Countrey) I con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſcended to returne vnto the Pope agayne, and then God with-drawing from me his grace: I was not ſo well minded before, as I became nought &amp; corrupt afterward, nor did not ſo well acknowledge a truthe, ſhew a repentaunce, and make a ſubmiſſion: as I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured afterward to heape lye vpon lye, in ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of my ſelfe, in defending the Pope, and in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dooing of all the good which before I had doone. In the which minde, after that I had framed an Epiſtle vnto her Ma. for to excuſe the Pope, his Seminarie Prieſts, and to father ſlaunders on my ſelfe &amp; other men, and had written an Apologie and other Libels to that effect, I was ſpeedilie conuaied out of the Realme, thinking firſt to haue trauailed to <hi>Rheames,</hi> and afterwarde to <hi>Rome.</hi> And directing firſt my courſe into <hi>Scotlande,</hi> (for that I feared to finde anie ſecure paſſage at any Engliſh Porte) I came to <hi>Leeth</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:27169:18"/> of purpoſe, there to take ſhypping for <hi>Fraunce,</hi> but finding no paſſage readie, I tooke the next oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie offered mee in a Flie-boate to <hi>Hamborough,</hi> in the which after I had ſayled fiue or ſixe daies, and comming neere vnto lande, behold, there happened ſuch a ſuddaine tempeſt &amp; ſtorme, that neither Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Mariner, or paſſenger, thought euer that hee ſhold haue eſcaped drowning. I ſeeing the immine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perrill and danger, I called to memorie the dyſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient fact of <hi>Ionas,</hi> who beeing commaunded of God to goe vnto <hi>Nin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uie,</hi> tranſported himſelfe towardes <hi>Tharſis:</hi> who with the like tempeſt was puniſhed of almightie GOD for his tranſgreſſion; I applyed the example vnto my ſelfe, I thought I had gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſlie offended in forſaking my Countrey, &amp; falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying my faith vnto GOD and my Prince I vowed, that if it would pleaſe God to deliuer mee from that preſent danger, and to ſaue the whole company that they might not perriſh for mee, I woulde deſiſt my purpoſed iourney, and returne againe into Englande with what perril ſoeuer. To be ſhort, it pleaſed God to heare my petition wee came ſafe to <hi>Hamborough,</hi> where after I had remained awhile, I repayred vnto her Ma. Comiſſioners that were come thether, who can beare witnes of my repentaunce. Not long after, I came back of mine owne accord into England, and ſubmitted my ſelfe vnto her Maieſties mercie. Her highnes graciouſlie pardoned mine offence, and ſo was I reſtored vnto grace againe, and this was the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time.</p>
                  <p>Good Lord, what ſhould be the cauſe of my fall againe? <hi>O altitudo diuitiarum ſapientiae et ſcientiae Dei. O wonderfull depth of Gods profounde Iuſtice and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> My time was not yet come that I was to bee called effectuallie, ſomething yet remained that God
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27169:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> would haue perfected and doone, for the further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of his glorie, for the which hee permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me to fall more miſerably the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before I had done. And like as <hi>Peter</hi> became worſe &amp; worſe in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of his Maiſter, and neuer repented him vntyll Chriſt looked backe vppon him againe: euen ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came I worſe then euer before I had beene, and was paſt all hope almoſt of repentaunce, had not Chriſt looked backe vppon me in the very laſt moment of time: for being fallen into the peruerſitie of my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer opinion, neither feare of death, ſhame of the world, long impriſonment, could once alter mee, but if I had beene called vnto my tryall anie time within halfe a yeere after, I had I thinke, died as obſtinatlie as anie before me had doone. Howe it pleaſed God at the laſt to conuert me, I haue ſet downe in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation, I neede not heere report it againe, &amp; thus much I thought good to make a ſupplie of that, which if time had permitted me, ſhoulde haue beene deliuered at ſuch time as I made my publike recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: the which once I had thought altogether to haue concealed, but that I remembred, that <hi>Secretum Regis abſcondere, bonum eſt, opera autem Dei reuelare, honorificum:</hi> that is, <hi>To conceale the ſecret of the King, is a good thing, but to manifeſt the wonderfull workes of almightie God, is a moſt honorable thing.</hi> Now come I to the ſecond cauſe, to giue thee (Gentle Reader) a fuller ſatisfaction, that my former recantation hath beene doone without all hypocriſie or dyſſimulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>As my recantation was publicke, and before an honourable, worſhipfull, and woorthy aſſembly, ſo I hope that their harts were ſo mooued, that moſt of them we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e enclined vnto pittie &amp; compaſſion, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, ſuch as heard me not, &amp; ſhall onely peruſe this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27169:19"/> dombe Letter. I knowe not howe they may ſtande perſwaded of my true and faithfull meaning, and the more hardlie they may be incenſed againſt me, when perhaps they ſhall heare of my former Lybelles and Letters written in the defence of the Pope, and all Seminarie Prieſts, at ſuch time as I was returned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pope again; that hauing written ſo veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in their behalfe, in reproofe of my ſelfe and myne owne confeſſions, with proteſtations that all that I had doone, was but in deepe hypocriſie &amp; dyſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: and now affirming the cleene contrary, may yet ſuſpect me of double dealing, and ſtand in doubt what to beleeue. For if I did ſaie true then, I muſt diſſemble now: and if I ſaie true now, I coulde not but write falſhoode then. For thy better ſatisfaction in this point (good Chriſtian Reader) leaſt thy good opinion of mee might be carried awaie by the frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent practiſe of the enemie againe, I haue ſette downe the true cauſes that moued me firſt to reiect the Pope, hoping that they be ſuch, as no honeſt or good man may denie them: which beeing found to be true in the ſight and knowledge of euery man, I leaue it then for the indifferent Reader to iudge, whether I had iuſt cauſe to forſake the Pope as I did, &amp; whether I haue written anie ſlaunder againſt him. His dooings beeing far worſe then that I haue alreadie ſpoken, and whether I had good cauſe to ſuſpect his religion, ſith that our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>That euerie Tree is knowne by his fruite,</hi> and the fruites that the Pope yeeldeth, beeing nothing els but horrible practiſes and Treaſons, I ſee not but that the Tree (as I ſaid in my recantation) together with the body and braunches, is to be hewen downe.</p>
                  <p>As for my Lybels and writings that I haue pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and made in his defence, the more they rome
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27169:19"/> with proteſtations, the more a wiſe man hath cauſe to ſuſpect them; for ſurelie they come all from that foule ſpirit which firſt was throwne out, and beeing returned againe, he brought ſeauen worſe then him ſelfe to hold more ſure poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But conſider (good Chriſtian Reader) the wonderfull power and mercy of almightie GOD, in this one onely thing. Had I beene aſſured that I had ſetled my former fayth and Religion vppon a ſtable grounde, had not my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cryed out againſt mee, at what time the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of GOD did effectuallie touch mee, woulde I (thinke you) after that I had wilfully forſaken the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours and mercies of my Prince, the libertie of my Countrey, the poſſibilitie of preferments, and after I had ſo deſperatlie committed my ſelfe vnto the open ſhame and obloquie of the world, to the daunger of death, &amp; in the extreamitie of ſicknes when I could hope for no life, haue repented mee of that which I had doone, and make ſuch a ditection of my faulte, &amp; ſuch a publique recantation as I haue doone, veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie I thinke no wiſe or reaſonable man woulde euer thinke it; and therfore, if this be not a ſufficient and a ſtrong argument to prooue my vnfained repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, I can but crie with the Prophet, <hi>Iudica me Deus, er diſcerne cauſam meam, Iudge me O Lorde, and dyſcerne my cauſe.</hi> I can but referre the matter vnto thee heauenlie Iudge, that in the latter day muſt iudge me and all man kinde: and thus much touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fulnes of ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>Now laſtlie I thought good to ſette out this Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face for to encounter the enemie, who as I heare, hath publiſhed in Print my former Lybels, ſubſcry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with mine owne hande, for the which I giue by theſe preſents al the world to vnderſtand, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I haue written heeretofore in the defence of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27169:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Pope, it hath beene in the time of my ſeduction, in the zeale of Papiſtrie, and therefore thoſe wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings are not to bee regarded of anie wiſe or godlie perſon. And truelie the Papiſts haue deceiued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the publiſhing of thoſe Pamphlets: for, if Charitie coulde not haue perſwaded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to conceale them, me thinkes that policie ſhoulde, for they doe but miniſter matter vnto me to aunſwer them, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſhall be conſtrained to lay open their nakednes, which otherwiſe I thought to haue couered, &amp; they heape moe coales on their owne heads then they bee aware of. I ſaie no more at this time, vntill I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand further what they haue doone. And thus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing abſolued ſo much as I thought neceſſarie to ad by waie of Praeface, I doe referre thee (gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) vnto the Recantation it ſelfe, crauing pardon if I haue troubled thee ouer long. From my cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at S. Katherins the 31. of Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <hi>Anno. Domi. 1588.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your paenitent Countryman and wel-willer in the Lorde, Anthony Tyrrell.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:27169:20"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The recantation or abiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Anthonie Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell: &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious &amp; outragious treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, after ſo many mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull remiſſions, that not many monthes paſſed, I publiquelie committed at this place (right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, worſhipfull, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued) in the diſperſing of certaine infamous Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, to the great diſhonor of almighty GOD, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of true Religion, diſpleaſure of my Prince, ſcandall and offence vnto all good and godly Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, reioycing of Gods enemies, and mine own eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall rebuke and infamie: I was a fearde leaſt that my name for euer had béene blotted out of the Booke of life, and that no place had béene left mee in thys world for true repentance.</p>
                  <p>But beholde, ſuch hath béene the effect, as I hope, of ſome mens good prayers, ſuch hath béene the great fauour ſhewed me, in the tolleration of my leude and haynous fact, ſuch hath béene the excéeding clemencie of my gracious Prince and Soueraigne: but aboue all, ſuch hath béene the infinite mercie of almighty GOD, in the renuing and perfecting this act of my conuerſion, that I doo not onely inwardlie féele an aſſured hope of Gods euerlaſting pardon &amp; forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but outwardly alſo, I ſéeme to ſée a moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27169:21"/> reſemblaunce that all you, which haue had iuſt cauſe to hate and contemne me, will yet be moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with compaſſion.</p>
                  <p>May it pleaſe you therefore to vnderſtande, that I am come hether (as GOD is my witnes) not of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie compulſion, or for feare of any temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or hope of worldly preferment: much leſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced thereunto by anie falſe hypocriſie or diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but onely the frée mercy of almightie GOD ſo moouing me to confeſſe my fault, to craue forgiuenes, to renounce thoſe errors that I haue holden &amp; mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from my childhoode, of the Sinaguoge of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than (I meane of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) and to reu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite my ſelfe vnto the auncient Catholique and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique Church of Chriſt, whereof this Church of England is a part, béeing purged and reformed of all heriſie, Idolatrie, and ſuperſtition.</p>
                  <p>But, leaſt you ſhoulde meruaile by what wylfull follie I was ſeduced, or rather by what madnes I was mooued to fall into that Apoſtacie, hauing twiſe before renounced the Pope, that I woulde ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentlie returne vnto him againe: To yéeld you ſome ſatiſ-faction in that point, theſe may bee alſo to lette you vnderſtand, that the chéefeſt cauſe, as néere as I can coniecture, was the wonderfull prouidence of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD, who ſuffered mee to fall into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found depth of all iniquitie, that the bottomles depth of my extreame miſerie, might call and cry for ſuccor and helpe vnto the bottomleſſe depth of Gods infinit mercie, and that out of that huge heape and maſſe of ſinne, ſhame and confuſion, wherein moſt miſerablie I had enwrapped my ſelfe, he might pick out matter for to ſet foorth the honor and glory of his holy name. For ſuch is the goodnes of almightie God, that he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth no euill ſo great to be committed, but that hee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27169:21"/> worketh out ſome great goodnes of the ſame, eyther in ſhewing his iuſt iudgment and iuſtice in the puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of ſinne, or his excéeding mercie and clemencie in the pardoning of ſinne, or his omnipotent power, that he alone out of ſuch euill cauſes, is able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce theſe notable and good effects.</p>
                  <p>Perhaps alſo he would that I ſhould be an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto other men of his iuſtice and of his mercie: of his iuſtice, that no man preſume of his owne power and ſtrength, leaſt that he fal as miſerably as I haue doone: of his mercie, that no man diſpayre, bee hys offences neuer ſo gréeuous and manie, for were hee drowned and dead in ſinne, GOD is able to reuiue him againe (as hee hath doone me) whoſe name bee prayſed for euermore.</p>
                  <p>Let me yet if you pleaſe, adde another cauſe which more properlie concerneth my ſelfe, which was mine owne peruerſe and corrupt affection. For béeing by the great mercie of almightie God, ſafely brought out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> and that mine eyes were opened, &amp; that I did behold &amp; ſée the manie deformities of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet corrupt affection, brought mee to gyue eare vnto falſe perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and falſe perſwaſion made me moſt miſerablie with <hi>Lots</hi> wife to looke backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. For hauing béene brought vp all the dayes of my life in Papiſtrie, and trained in the Schooles of the Papiſts, whereby my knowledge was greatlie peruerted with the groundes of their Religion, it could not be, but that I muſt néedes bee infected with a great contagion, and according vnto the ſaying of the Poet: <hi>Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horat.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeruabit odorem teſta diu: <hi>With what liquor a new veſſell firſt is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, of the ſame it will haue a taſte a long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                     </hi> So, my veſſell, hauing in mine infancie euen to theſe late yéeres, béene filled with no other liquor
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27169:22"/> then that I had drunke out of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> I was the more eaſily corrupted when I did fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the companie of Papiſts againe. And not beeing ſo thankfull vnto almighty GOD for the benefite of his grace as I ſhould, nor ſo carefull to conſerue my ſelfe from the danger of ſinne: out of one ſin GOD ſuffered me to fall into another, inſomuch as <hi>peccatum</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part <hi>eſt cauſa et paena alterius peccati:</hi> one ſin is the cauſe and puniſhment of another: and beeing fallen into an extreame obſtinacie, with what furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous madnes I came hether vnto the Croſſe, it is not vnknowne, howe héere I behaued my ſelfe, there were many eye witneſſes, from hence I was carried vnto Newgate, where I gloried in that I had doone, from thence vnto the Counter in Woodſtréet, where I remained twentie foure wéekes cloſe pryſoner in that obſtinacie, that no perſwaſion or good entreatie could conuert me: in ſo much as if in all that time I had béene called vnto my tryall, as many of my qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and condition haue béene, I thinke verilie that I had ended my life as obſtinatlie as any of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sed nouit Dominus qui ſunt eius, <hi>GOD knoweth who are his choſen,</hi>
                     </hi> and whome God hath determined to ſaue, no man can take from him.</p>
                  <p>Behold, I was during the time of mine impry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, viſited by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand of God with an extreame ſicknes, I languiſhed of the infirmitie vnto the verie death: for, ſo manie as did beholde me in my greate maladie, thought that I ſhoulde neuer haue eſcaped with life: at that time, I hadde all the conſolations and comforts that Papiſts could yéeld mee, and ſome that ſhal be nameles, comforted me with the Popes pardons &amp; Indulgences, ſaying: that I was a happy man, and that my name ſhould be memorable among the Papiſts when I were dead and gone.</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:27169:22"/>
                  <p>But all theſe conſolations at that time, coulde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all comfort mee: I remembred what was written, <hi>Maledictus homo qui confidit in homine, <hi>Curſed is hee that putteth his truſt in man, and hath not his confidence in God alone.</hi>
                     </hi> It pleaſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde to touch me with remorſe, I lifted vp my ſoule vnto Ieſus Chriſt the Sauiour of mankind: I cried with the Prophet <hi>Dauid, <hi>Peccaui:</hi>
                     </hi> and behold, <hi>Tranſtulit Dominus peccatum meum, <hi>God hath pardoned &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen me my ſinne:</hi>
                     </hi> and therefore I may verie well conclude with the Prophet, and ſay: <hi>A Domino fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt iſtud, et eſt mirabile in oculis noſtris, <hi>Thys is the Lords dooing, and it is meruailous in our eyes.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus haue you hearde a breefe confeſſion of my fault, the cauſes of my fall, and the wonderfull mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of almightie God in rayſing me vp againe. May it pleaſe you with the like patience, to fauoure mee in hearing of the reſt, and I ſhall diſpatch it with al the breuitie that I can.</p>
                  <p>And firſt of all as touching mine errours that I haue to renownce. I muſt confeſſe that I did neuer holde any in perticuler, but thoſe generall groundes of falſe doctrine which all Papiſts for the moſt parte doo holde, which for that they are many and almoſte innumerable, I knowe not better where I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin then by ſetting the Axe vnto the roote of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Trée, that euery Tree that bringeth not foorth good fruite, together with the body and braunches may bee hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en downe.</p>
                  <p>The Trée of all iniquitie is the Pope, the roote from whence ſpringeth all falſe doctrine, hereſie and ſedition, is his vſurped Primacie. For, whilſt hee may gouerne like a God vppon earth, hee forgetteth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat there is any God in heauen. Hys pryde in thys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oint is too intollerable, for he clymeth with <hi>Lucifer</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:27169:23"/> aboue the Heauens, inſomuch as the ſaying of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> may very well bee applyed vnto hym, which although it be meant of <hi>Nabuchodonozor,</hi> yet is it not vnproperly applyed vnto this his Coſen Germaine, the wordes are theſe: <hi>Aſcendam ſuper al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinem nubium, et ſimilis ero altiſsimo: <hi>I will aſcende aboue the height of the Clowdes, and I will bee like vnto the moſt higheſt.</hi>
                     </hi> Who aſcendeth aboue the Clowdes if not the Pope, who extendeth his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie aboue the Heauens? Dooth not hee alone cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize Saints? Doth not he alone make Martyrs, bee they neuer ſo rancke and wicked Traytors? He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth himſelfe coequall with GOD, in forgiuing and pardoning of ſinne, hee alone hath power and authority to cenſure the holy Scriptures, for they are not Canonicall without his making: they may haue no other interpretation but of his allowing. His De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crées, Definitions, Traditions and Ceremonies, are of equall credit with the holy Scripture, for wee are bounde to beléeue them vpon paine of damnation, as well as the other. Hee alone hath the kéeping of the Churches Treaſure, which, as they ſay, conſiſteth of the merits of Chriſt and of his Saints: wherein hée committeth an horrible blaſphemie, to make the Saints coparteners with Chriſt in the act of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. What ſhall néede many wordes, he is the contayner of all trueth, he cannot erre, ſo that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Papiſts fayth doth depende vppon the Pope alone. If any Papiſt doo obiect and ſay, that I ſay vntruelie, for that they grounde their Fayth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the definition of the Church, I woulde but aſke them what Church they meane, ſurely they meane not the vniuerſall Church of Chriſt, but the perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (if that may be called a Church that is infected with ſo great a contagion) and who I
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27169:23"/> pray you is the Gouernour and Ruler of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churche but the Pope alone? As for the Generall Counſels whereof they bragge ſo much, it is a moſt vaine and friuolous thing. For no Counſell can be called with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Popes ſommoning, and no Counſell can bee of authority without his confirming: ſo that the full reſolution of any doubt in doctrine dependeth vppon the Pope alone, be he neuer ſo vnlearned, neuer ſo wicked a man.</p>
                  <p>O vnhappy Church that reſteth vpon ſuch a one. From hence procéeded all my errours in doctrine whatſoeuer: for, whilſt I grounded my fayth vppon the authoritie of the Pope, I had ſmall regarde or none at all vnto the holy Scripture, I cared not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I wanted prooues for my doctrine out of the worde of GOD, it was ſufficient that I coulde ſay thus it is ſet downe by the Pope, thus wee muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue: and therefore the Popes Diuinitie may well be called poſitiue, for it is ſet downe after his owne faſhyon. From hence, procéeded my error of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe, that it was a ſacrifice propitiatorie for the quick and the dead. From hence, my error of tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Sacrament of the Lords Supper was to he adminiſtred vnto the Laie people vnder one kind, That the publique ſeruice of the Church was to be celebrat in an vnknowne tongue. That there were fiue Sacraments more then euer Chriſte did inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute. From hence, procéeced my doctrine of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, Pardons, Prayer for the dead and ſatiſ-facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. From hence, inuocation of Saints, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, and Pylgrimages did procéede, with many other abſurdities too long héere to repeate. Let it ſuffiſe, I beſeeche you, that in one worde I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nownce the Pope and all his doctrine, who for that hee hath mounted ſo high with the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:27169:24"/> it cannot be but that the like pryde wil haue the like like fall, and therefore I wyll recyte but hys fall, and there I will leaue him. It followeth in the Prophet, <hi>Veruntamen ad infernum detraheris, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundum laci, <hi>Notwithſtanding, thou ſhalt be drawne downe to hell vnto the bottome of the Lake:</hi>
                     </hi> from the which good Lorde deliuer mee and all good men. And thus much of my errors that I doo renounce.</p>
                  <p>Hauing by Gods prouidence emptied my veſſell of this vnſauorie liquor, may it pleaſe you in a word to vnderſtand, what liquor I haue receiued in, (for as the Philoſopher ſayth: <hi>Non eſt vacu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m in rerum natura,</hi>) The liquor therefore that I haue receiued ſurely is no other, then that which I haue drawne out of the pure Fountayne of Gods moſt holie word. And I beléeue that all things neceſſary for mans ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, are ſufficiently contained in Gods moſt holie word, and that no man is bound to beléeue as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of hys Fayth, any other doctrine then is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in holy Scripture, or by neceſſary conſequence may be deduced out of the ſame. And becauſe I would not ſéeme to be carried from hence foorth wyth anye perticuler ſpyrite, I doo firmely aſſent vnto all thoſe Articles of Religion which haue béene ſet downe by the common conſent of the learned Clergie of thys Realme, vnto the which, for that I doo find them in all poynts agréeable vnto Gods moſt holy worde, I haue moſt willingly ſubſcribed, and ſhall defend them God wylling, againſt all the aduerſaries whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. And thus much as touching my preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe of doctrine.</p>
                  <p>Nowe laſtly it remaineth, that I doo aſke perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer and publique forgiuenes according to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt whom, and according to the quallitie of the offence wherein I haue offended. And heere I
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27169:24"/> muſt confeſſe to the greater honor of almighty God, that I haue had manie and vehement temptations to hinder me from this action of repentaunce, but the temptations béeing but worldly and fleſhly, with the ſword of Gods ſpirit I haue cut them a ſunder vnto nothing, and againſt the ſhame of the worlde I haue learned to ſay, <hi>Melius eſt confundi in hoc ſaeculo, quam in futuro, <hi>Better it is to be confounded in this world, then in the worlde to come.</hi>
                     </hi> And againſt pryde and haughtines of minde, (the which temptations dyd much moleſt me) I haue learned to ſay with <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, <hi>Melior eſt in malis factis humilis confeſsio, quam in bonis, ſuperba gloriatio,</hi> Better it is when a man hath doone euil, humblie to confeſſe his fault, then proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to vaunt of any good deed.</hi> And rather I had with the penitent Publican confeſſe my ſelfe an open ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then with the proude Phariſey to proue my ſelfe a lyer.</p>
                  <p>I doo therefore in all humilitie proſtrate my ſelfe firſt before the mercy ſeate of the omnipotent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, crauing pardon and forgiuenes from the bottom of my hart for my many ſinnes and offences. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, my gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Lady and dread Soueraigne, whoſe great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and clemencie towards mee, I haue ouermuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed. Firſt, by liuing fifteene yeeres beyonde the Seas among her Maieſties profeſſed enemies, and foure yeres hauing béene of the <hi>Romaine</hi> Seminary, from whence I was ſent by the Pope and the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites into this her Maieſties Realme. Eyght yeeres I haue conuerſed and raunged vppe and down with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her Maieſties Dominions as a Seminary prieſt, (except ſome ſmall time that I had beene in pryſon) to ſowe the ſeede of ſedition &amp; of falſe doctrine, and to gaine as many of her Maieſties Subiects vnto the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27169:25"/> Pope as I coulde. Yet muſt I proteſt that I coulde neuer in my life be induced to conſent vnto any trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous practiſe againſt her Maieſties perſon, and that alwaies it gréeued mee, when I did heare her Maieſtie miſtermed, or vnreuerently ſpoken of at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie time. I muſt confeſſe that I was priuie vnto a great part of the Treaſon of <hi>Ballard</hi> and <hi>Babyngton,</hi> and I diſcouered my knowledge thereof vnto an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Counſeller of this Realme: but, after that I was fallen vnto the Pope againe, for the ſauing of his credite and his Seminarie Prieſtes, I denyed all againe, and therfore I doo craue of her Maieſty par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and forgiuenes againe and againe.</p>
                  <p>Thirdlie, I aſke forgiuenes of the right reuerend Father in God, my Lord Archbiſhoppe of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie his grace, for that I haue abuſed his fatherly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with deepe dyſſimulation.</p>
                  <p>Fourthlie, I moſt humblie craue pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right honorable my eſpeciall good Lord, the Lorde high Treaſurer of England, whoſe godlie expectation of me, by my ſiniſter and leude dealinges I haue ouermuch abuſed, and yet his honor alwaies recompenſed myne euill with good againe.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, I craue pardon and forgiuenes of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, worſhipfull, and worthy aſſemblie. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, of all the world, and eſpecially of all my déere and louing Countreymen, and thoſe whom I haue anie manner of waies deceiued with anie corrupt or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe doctrine, praying GOD to conuert them as he hath conuerted me, that I with them, and they with me, may liue together in the Kingdome of Heauen. Moſt humbly beſéeching you, right honorable, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull and the reſt, to open the bowels of your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſyon to me, and that you wold not ſo much reſpect what mannner of man I haue béene, as to conſider
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:27169:25"/> what nowe by the grace of GOD I am, and by the ſame grace ſhall ſo continue.</p>
                  <p>If it may pleaſe you to vouchſafe me this my firſt petition, that euer I requeſted at your hands in this publique manner, I ſhalbe ſo carefull by Gods grace to conſerue ſo great a benefite, as I hope neuer to trouble you in the like againe.</p>
                  <p>It pleaſed GOD the laſt Sunday, to reioyce your harts at the conuerſion of a ſinner, which ioy that then was made, did repreſent the ioy in Heauen. I hope that he ſhall reioyce your harts againe to day, and I pray God you may ſo reioyce your harts euery day, vntill wee come vnto that compleat and perfect ioy, where we may ioy for euer, and ſay, <hi>Haec eſt dies quam fecit Dominus, exultemus et laetemur in ea, <hi>This is the daie which the Lord hath made, let vs reioyce &amp; be merrie therein.</hi>
                     </hi> God that hath enclyned my harte vnto repentaunce, I hope wil alſo encline your harts to yéelde forgiuenes. To his Maieſtie, béeing thrée perſons in Trinitie and one in vnitie, be all honour, prayſe, glorie and dominion, bothe nowe and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Haec omnia ſuperſcripta vere et non ficte, ex animo et corde fuiſſe dicta, teſtis eſt mihi Deus: manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que propria ſunt exarata. <hi>Anthonius Tyrrell.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
